Okay, so we begin now the the eighth פרק, perek, האישה. Haisha.
Let's take a look. The woman. So we begin it פ"ז עמוד
א', Peh Zayin Amud Aleph, top of the page.
האישה בזמן שהיא בבית בעלה. Haisha bizman shehi beveis baalah. One of
the things we haven't spoken about by the קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach,
we've alluded to once or twice, by the way, we've actually referred
to once or twice, but have not really had a focused conversation,
is women's obligation in the קרבן פסח. Korban Pesach. So since we
were talking about חבורה, chabura, this משנה mishna starts with the question
about which group to assume that the that a certain that a
woman is part of, a wife, who is also a daughter. Which
group is she part of? But we will also get to conversations
about a woman's obligation in the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach itself. So
we start the following: האישה בזמן שהיא בבית בעלה. Haisha bizman shehi
beveis baalah. If a woman is in her husband's house,
so שחט עליה בעלה, shachat aleha baalah, her husband שוחט shechts the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach with her in mind, ושחט עליה אביה, veshachat
aleha aviha, and her father does the same thing. So תאכל משל
בעלה. tochal mishel baalah. It's assumed that she wants to be with
her husband and therefore, although both the husband and the father wanted
her to be with her, it's assumed that she wants to be
with her husband and therefore she is part of that group. Now,
what's interesting about this, besides the question about what do we assume
her preference is, is how does one become part of a group
of a קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, right? Do you have to it
sounds like she didn't chip in any money. Okay, is there a
formal process of of like, you know, taking down a list of
names? It's that I think is something that definitely needs to be
explored that is particularly raised here. Just I had it in mind,
you had it in mind, your assumed preference. What exactly defines what
what makes you part of the group?
Is this also an issue of זכין לאדם שלא בפניו? zachin leadam
shelo bifanav?
It could be.
I don't know, we're going to have to look.
Yeah, yeah, I mean that's certainly true. But yes, I mean זכין,
zachin, but but it's not clear that actual an act of קנין
kinyan was done. It sounds like it's just a sense of what
was in your head. So that's something to explore about what makes
you part of the group.
Okay, also want to explore...
Yeah, yeah, let's just no, not about that. Let's I mean it's
a similar issue to which house she's part of. Let's keep on
going. Okay now, תאכל משל בעלה. tochal mishel baalah. הלכה רגל ראשון
לעשות בבית אביה. halcha regel rishon laasos beveis aviha.
Now, let's say on the first פסח Pesach she actually went to
her father's
house without her husband or yeah, I don't know, she left her
house, 'I'm going to my father's house, you come if you want'
or something. We'll see, it's not clear. So then, in that case,
שחט עליה אביה ושחט עליה בעלה. shachat aleha aviha veshachat aleha baalah.
Her husband her father is שוחט shechting the פסח Pesach for her
and her father and her husband does. תאכל במקום שהיא רוצה. tochal
bimakom shehi rotza. Then it's less clear who she wants to be
with for יום טוב Yom Tov and therefore she eats where she
wants. Now of course part of the question is it sounds like
what she tells us later retroactively will determine and that's the גמרא's
Gemara question of ברירה. breira. But the other question here is what
what are we talking about? Are we talking about the same יום
טוב Yom Tov she went to spend with her father's house? It's
not clear where she wants to be? Or if on יום טוב
Yom Tov one she went to her father's house, then on יום
טוב Yom Tov two it's an open question. Again, a lot of
things not clear in this משנה. mishna. Right, but wherever father's staying,
but they they both live in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. I mean wherever...
No, but they don't, they can get together.
They could, but they're but that's not the case. The גמרא Gemara
is bringing this up קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, that's not the case.
Which רגל ראשון? regel rishon? Is it the following year?
That's what I said, that is not clear. Does it mean that
on this רגל regel itself where she went to her father's house,
it's still not clear where she wants to eat her קרבן פסח?
Korban Pesach? Or no, if on the first רגל regel and who
maybe the רגל regel wasn't even פסח? Pesach? Maybe it was סוכות
Sukkos she went to her father's house, maybe she's indicated that she
likes spending יום טוב Yom Tov in her father's house.
So for the first time...
Or the first time it happened. A lot of things are not
clear. Okay now, יתום ששחטו עליו
אפוטרופסין. yasom sheshachtu alav apitropsin. Now,
you have an orphan who has two caretakers, אפוטרופסין, apitropsin, people that
really are more there's a better word, guard... Yeah, but it's not
as much guardians over them as much as over their property. So
I'm I'm trying to think of trustees of the estate or executors
of the estate, executors of the estate. Anyway, people that are that
are but to some degree responsible for them as well. And there's
more than one. And each one brought a קרבן פסח Korban Pesach
thinking that he was going to include the orphan with his פסח.
Pesach. But each of the trustees or whatever guardians did a different
brought a different קרבן. korban. So יאכל במקום שהוא רוצה. yochal bimakom
shehu rotze. He eats where he wants. Okay again, the question is
how do doesn't it have to be determined at the time of
the שחיטה? shechita? We'll see. עבד של שני שותפין. Eved shel shenei
shutfin. We'll go the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss all this.
עבד של שני שותפין, eved shel shenei shutfin, if you have a
slave who has two owners, a part owned in partnership, לא יאכל
משל שניהם. lo yochal mishel sheneihem. He cannot eat from either of
theirs and even if one of them and even if one of
the masters and the slave explicitly says, right, ראובן Reuven says, 'I'm
having the slave eat with me,' and the slave says, 'Yeah, I
want to eat with ראובן,' Reuven, he's not allowed to. Why? Because
he's also שמעון's Shimon slave and שמעון Shimon you can't do anything
without without both partners agreeing. And we'll see why in the גמרא.
Gemara. But if both agree, of course it's fine. But even if
the preferences have been explicitly stated, it cannot be done without both
of them agreeing. מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין, Mi shechetzio eved
vechetzio ben chorin, now somebody who's half slave and half free,
לא יאכל. lo yochal. with his master because we don't assume although
we normally assume that a master wants is going to have his
slave eat with him and by the way the whole idea of
slaves eating with their masters is clear in the פסוקים pesukim about
the פסח pesach right about the about when you circumcise your slaves
right then they can eat from it the assumption that slaves are
eating with their masters but if this person had how do you
have somebody who's half free he's owned by partners and one of
them frees him so in that case you can't take it for
granted that the master wants this person to eat with him because
this person is not fully his slave
can he eat his own or does he have to master
alright all of that to be discussed as we get in as
we get into the okay I'm glad you have so many questions
that's what we have a גמרא Gemara for let's take a look
at the גמרא Gemara שמע מינא shma mina says the גמרא Gemara
we can infer from this entire משנה mishna that when it allows
the preference to be determined later that יש ברירה yesh breira that
there is retroactive determination right ברירה breira is an idea that when
you determine something later we say retroactively that that we can assume
that that was the status or that was the way things were
going to be from the from the outset so who cares if
this woman decided you know after the קרבן korban was brought it's
too late who cares if this orphan decided after the קרבן korban
was brought it's too late so the גמרא Gemara says no מאי
רוצה mai rotza what does it mean where the woman decides or
where the orphan decides בשעת שחיטה beshat shechita means that they've expressed
their preference you know at the moment before the שחיטה shechita took
place so when there is a question husband or father which of
the caretakers in those cases they have to express their preference beforehand
and if they didn't so if you look at תוספות Tosafot if
we really hold אין ברירה ein breira and they didn't express the
preference then we don't know which group she's a part of and
we learned before you can't eat from a פסח pesach you're not
a part of so תוספות Tosafot says מאי רוצה בשעת שחיטה mai
rotza beshat shechita if you look at תוספות Tosafot it says דוקא
בירורה בשעת שחיטה davka beirura beshat shechita אבל לא בירורה aval lo
beirura if there was no preference expressed and we are assuming אין
ברירה ein breira אינו אוכל לא משל זה ולא משל זה eino
ochel lo mishel zeh velo mishel zeh can't eat either because you
don't know which group you're a part of and you can't eat
both because you can't eat you know כגון כפרה על החבורה k'gon
kapara al hachabura or he's eating from the פסח pesach you're not
a part of so you're really stuck okay so that but the
but that's the simple sense of the משנה mishna is not that
way but if we want to assume אין ברירה ein breira that's
what we have to say now the גמרא Gemara talks about
the משנה mishna says that she could eat with the
בעל ba'al right what the
רישא reisha no רישא reisha is when she's not she didn't spend
the first the first רגל regel at her father's house that's when
you assume that she's going to be with her husband okay now
the גמרא Gemara looks at this issue yes
they're saying that if both the father and the husband had the
intention to
include her
but she didn't
and she wasn't thinking
of it then
she's out of it unless she brings her own but if she
hasn't and she can express a preference but if she hasn't expressed
her preference or brought her own then you can't assume she's part
of either group okay
but the משנה mishna sounds like both both the father and the
husband already שחטו עליה shachatu aleha right
so that's why it's a very weak read of the משנה mishna
it says right the read is the read is right if it's
שחט במקום שהיא רוצה shachat bimkom she'hi rotza means right the simple
absolutely the simple sense of the משנה mishna is she decides after
the שחיטה shechita and retroactively that determined and that's the principle of
ברירה breira so although there are opinions יש ברירה yesh breira the
גמרא Gemara is saying that the way to read this משנה mishna
and not be put into that corner would be to say she
had already decided but there's no question it is not the simple
sense of the משנה mishna right absolutely okay so we don't know
okay let's take a look now we continue okay
רמינהי remini and
why are they doing that why are they so uncomfortable about it
why are they with you know
oh the גמרא Gemara is always like that the גמרא Gemara the
גמרא Gemara wants to feel that if there's a if there's a
debate about something we you know we have to figure out how
each side can deal with all the evidence against them so we
try to just you know even if it means sometimes twisting the
simple sense of certain texts that's you know that's like otherwise there
wouldn't have been a debate if it was so clear although by
ברירה breira I must say it's a debate of תנאים tanna'im so
it wouldn't have been a big deal to say this is following
the תנא tanna that says that says יש ברירה yesh breira anyway
I know we'll let's let's wait till we get there okay we
have a big דף daf to do okay so it says like
this and a lot of the rest of the משנה mishna is
going to be explored now רמינהי remini I'll ask you on this
question about when is a woman assumed to you know take for
granted she wants to be with her husband when do we have
a doubt you know in our משנה mishna said the doubt comes
up when she spent the first רגל regel by her father's house
so the גמרא Gemara says I'll ask you on this אשה רגל
הראשון אוכלת משל אביה isha regel harishon ochelet mishel aviha here it
says that the first רגל regel you assume that she wants to
eat with her father and there's no doubt and be it's even
if she didn't go to her father's house you assume that the
first יום טוב yom tov she wants to go she wants to
be with her father מכאן ואילך mikan ve'eilach
afterwards רוצה אוכלת משל אביה רוצה אוכלת משל בעלה rotza ochelet mishel
aviha rotza ochelet mishel ba'alah then we're not sure where she wants
to go and that's when there's this doubt so actually this is
basically assuming much more of a doubt that there's a general assumption
of preference to the father certainly for the first יום טוב yom
tov and after It's more up in the air. I should say,
you know, that there's all this traditions when a couple gets married
like where are we spending the first יום טוב, Yom Tov, you
know, oh first יום טוב Yom Tov by your parents' house, next
יום טוב Yom Tov by my parents' house. So absolutely some of
that was already a case. It seems like that there was a
strong idea that רגלא רישון Regla Rishon was at least she went,
presumably I hope they both went, but anyway at least they were
going to her father's house the first יום טוב, Yom Tov, her
parents.
What? I always thought they were making that up.
When the people said that idea.
Yes, the daughter always goes to the first,
there here it is, long-standing practice.
תוספות Tosefot says that it seems she already goes to the father.
Shh, too many voices. Okay, Dov what were you saying?
And you can't ask her?
You can, right. Again, the assumption of course in the משנה Mishna
is notice, you know, that the woman is completely silent here, everybody's
making assumptions about her, and only when there's a question, you know,
does it sort of say that you have to find out what
she wants, but that's certainly the.
Or you would have to ask her before the שחיטה. Shechita.
Right, that you missed that. You came in with that.
Okay, so and תוספות Tosefot doesn't he say בברישא? Be-reisha?
That's what, yeah, let's not worry about that תוספות.
Tosefot. She's by the husband.
Let's not worry about תוספות. Tosefot. Let's find the גמרא. Gemara. Okay,
so anyway which is it? So our משנה Mishna assumes that you
know that generally with the husband, the ברייתא Braita assumes a more
of a leaning towards the father. So the גמרא Gemara says לא
קשיא, Lo Kashya, it's not difficult, כאן ברדופה לילך כאן בשאינה רדופה.
Kan be-redufa leilech kan be-she-eino redufa.
There's women that generally are always looking, are always, you know, running
back to their father's house, and there's those that are not so
much so, depends on the woman, whether we assume that she generally,
you know, that there might be a greater preference to be back
at the father's house. Again, I hope it's with the husband, but
anyway to go back there for יום טוב. Yom Tov. דכתיב, De-ksiv,
as the פסוק Pasuk says, אז הייתי בעיניו כמוצאת שלום. Az hayiti
be-einav kemotzet shalom.
Then I was in his eyes like someone who finds peace. What
does that mean? ואמר רבי יוחנן, Ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan, ככלה שנמצאת שלימה
בבית חמיה, Ke-khala she-nimtza'at sheleima be-veit chameha,
this is quite fascinatingly ironic based on what we would have expected.
Okay, like a bride who is found to be complete in her
father-in-law's house, meaning she's so loved there and welcomed and accepted and
everybody just speaks good about her. And what does she do? So
she's רוצה לילך להשביח בבית אביה. Rotzah leilech le-hashbi'ach be-veit aviha. She
goes back to her father's house to tell her father about how
much they love her. So that's quite ironic. Right, we would have
expected, who's the כלה Kalla who wants, I mean, A, obviously it
has to do with the whole family dynamics prior and how much,
you know, how much she likes spending יום טוב Yom Tov with
her parents, but we would, I think we would have assumed also
that if she's having a harder time with her in-laws, she's more
going back to her parents. The גמרא Gemara does a nice little
twist on it. Oh, you know why she's going back to her
parents? 'Cause they love her in her father-in-law's house. All right. Anyway,
but there are different types of, you know, obviously different scenarios, so
sometimes there's more of an open question and sometimes it's more taken
for granted that they're going to the father's house. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara gets onto a nice little digression. Okay, כתיב, Ksiv, not
כדכתיב, Ke-de-ksiv, כתיב. Ksiv. והיה ביום ההוא נאם ה' תקראי אישי ולא
תקראי לי עוד בעלי. Ve-haya ba-yom ha-hu neum Hashem tikrei Ishi ve-lo
tikrei li od Ba'ali. It'll be on that day you will call
me אישי, Ishi, your husband, and not your בעלי. Ba'ali. Now of
course the simple sense of the verse is והסירותי את שמות הבעלים
מפיה Ve-hasiroti et shemot ha-be'alim mi-piha because the בעל, Baal, בעלים Be'alim
were the idolatrous gods and therefore you won't refer to me as
בעל Baal which has an allusion to other gods. But of course
I think this verse is also nice because the בעלי Ba'ali has
a sense of, you know, of ownership, of בעל, Baal, right, of
sex, of ownership, and it's and whereas אישי Ishi is more of
a sense of equivalence and intimacy, exactly, so certainly it could be
a nice modern interpretation of this פסוק. Pasuk. Now let's see what
the גמרא Gemara does with it. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
what does that mean? ככלה בבית חמיה, Ke-khala be-veit chameha, like a
daughter-in-law and her or bride in her father-in-law's house. Interesting by the
way, I should say כלה Kalla also means daughter-in-law, right? So the
assumption is that the bride is with the groom's parents. I mean
again, you know, wasn't always that they had the money to start
their own household, so they would move in with the groom and
his parents, and that's why she's also the daughter-in-law. Anyway, the כלה
בבית חמיה Kalla be-veit chameha ולא ככלה בבית אביה, ve-lo ke-khala be-veit
aviha, not in her father's house. Which presumably again it's not at
all clear to me what this means. I mean it means she's
well loved in her in her in her
father-in-law's house and therefore she's אישי Ishi and not
בעלי Ba'ali and she's in her father's house, but I thought she
was in her father's house because she was well loved in her
in her, you know, so I don't exactly get what's going on
here.
I leave it open for any interpretation but I don't understand. We
just got through saying that if she's in בית אביה, Beit aviha,
that means she's the same רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right? It's the
same רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan just said that she was in בית
אביה Beit aviha is because right she's in בית אביה Beit aviha
it means that she's loved in her father-in-law's house and how it
ties into אישי Ishi and בעלי Ba'ali I don't know. I don't
know if Artscroll helps. Does Artscroll give any or or your Steinsaltz
any?
You're not a member of your family more,
yeah, and therefore she is, but not בית אביה. Beit aviha. But
again we just got through saying that בית אביה Beit aviha she
goes to בית אביה Beit aviha when to tell about how loved
she is in her in her
father-in-law's house.
I don't know. Of course. What? One we received in her father-in-law's
house.
One we received in her father, meaning as opposed to, but I
don't get as opposed to כלה בבית אביה. Kallah b'Beit Aviha. What
does that mean as opposed to? Meaning before she even got married?
That, yeah, that's actually what it says here in Steinsaltz, that she
was still...
So she's now in her father-in-law's house and she's been warmly received
as opposed to when she was had not yet left...
she would be
ארוסה, arusah, אזיין, azayin, then she wouldn't be בעלי, ba'ali, wouldn't use
בעלי ba'ali when she was an ארוסה. arusah.
All right, that would be בבית אביה. b'Beit Aviha. She's מאורסת me'ureset
אזיין azayin and she has no קרבה kirvah with her husband's family.
I know, so why is she being called בעלי? ba'ali? That makes
no sense. So anyway, I don't know. If somebody has a better
interpretation, I'll take it. But okay, moving on. Now, אחות לנו achot
lanu and now that we're talking about שיר השירים, Shir HaShirim, we
get to do a little, a little explication of שיר השירים. Shir
HaShirim.
אחות לנו קטנה, achot lanu k'tanah, we have a young sister, ושדיים
אין לה, v'shadayim ein lah, and she has no breasts. אמר רבי
יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו עילם zu Elam שזכתה ללמוד ולא שזכתה
ללמד, shezachatah lilmod v'lo zachatah l'lamed, עילם Elam which is where דניאל
Daniel went into גלות, galut, which is sort of near בבל Bavel
but not בבל. Bavel. So that's the young daughter. The older sister
is בבל, Bavel, okay, but עילם, Elam, that's had, people learned תורה
Torah there, דניאל Daniel was there, but no teachers of תורה Torah
ever came out from there, translating this whole thing in the...
meaning it wasn't nurturing.
It wasn't nurturing. It didn't give its milk exactly to others.
ושדיים v'shadayim זה תורה. zeh Torah.
תורה. Torah. This is all about תורה. Torah. Exactly. I got to
tell you, I don't know if people are aware of this, but
before Artscroll got into the business of doing גמרות Gemarot and, you
know, doing the excellent job that they do there, you know, they
had, they did translations
of ספרי תנ"ך. Sifrei Tanakh. And the Artscroll שיר השירים Shir HaShirim
is the funniest thing ever because it's not just they don't just
do commentary, the literal translation that they give on the פשט, peshat,
right, is basically something like this: "We have a sister, she has
not yet begun to teach Torah" or something. I don't know. I'd
have to check it, but it would be something like that. Okay,
now, אני חומה ושדי כמגדלות, ani chomah v'shadai k'migdalot,
I am like a wall and my breasts are like towers. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, again we're with רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
אני חומה זו תורה, ani chomah zu Torah, there you go explicitly,
that's the Torah. ושדי כמגדלות אלו תלמידי חכמים, v'shadai k'migdalot elu talmidei
chachamim,
those are the Torah sages which now again, does that mean that
they give protection? Is that supposed to be... that's what רש"י Rashi
says, שמגינים על הדור, shemeginim al hador, they give protection to the
city as opposed to the other imagery which was about nurturing. This
is about, you know, that their תורה Torah protects. ורבא
אמר, v'Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, אני חומה זו כנסת ישראל,
ani chomah zu Knesset Yisrael, it's the Jewish people. ושדי כמגדלות אלו
בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות, v'shadai k'migdalot elu batei knesiyot u'vatei midrashot,
these are the houses of the synagogues and the houses of study.
So that's a little bit more inclusive, right? It's not just about
תורה. Torah. It's about the entire Jewish people and about that their
institutions are not just the study halls but they're also the synagogues
as well.
And that's actually how Artscroll translated it: "The synagogues and study halls
are strong towers"...
oh you're looking at their English translation. Oh, because they have it
in their חומש? chumash? Ah.
What do they do with the other one about אחות לנו קטנה
ושדיים אין לה? achot lanu k'tanah v'shadayim ein lah? You can tell
us. All right, anyway, so, אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב,
amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia amar Rav, מאי דכתיב, mai d'chtiv, what's
meant by the
verse, אשר בנינו כנטיעים מגודלים בנעוריהם, asher baneinu k'neti'im megudalim bin'ureihem, our
sons are like young shoots that have, you know, that are growing
up in their youth, בנותינו כזויות מחוטבות תבנית היכל, binoteinu k'zaviyot mechutavot
tavnit heichal,
our daughters are like hewn cornerstones, cut, תבנית היכל, tavnit heichal, the
image of the castle or היכל heichal the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash.
So now we're going to interpret that verse. אשר בנינו כנטיעים אלו
בחורי ישראל שלא טעמו טעם חטא, asher baneinu k'neti'im elu bachurei Yisrael
shelo ta'amu ta'am chet,
these are the young men of Israel, you know, they're still children
and they have yet to have the taste of sin which presumably
means, which is presumably the context of sexual sin and means and
means not loss of
innocence, זרע לבטלה zera l'vatalah probably part of that consideration, so they're
still very young and they have yet to have, you know, הרהורים,
hirhurim, the גמרא Gemara is sort of very concerned about men and
their sexual thoughts and seminal emission. So that's they're still like young
shoots.
בנותינו כזויות, binoteinu k'zaviyot, and our daughters are like these cornerstones, אלו
בתולות ישראל שאוגדות פתחיהן לבעליהן, elu betulot Yisrael she'ogdot pitchieihen l'va'aleihen, these
are the young virgins among
Israel that close up their openings for their husbands, meaning that they
protect their virginity for their husbands. So it's sort of like the
parallel. So how do you get זויות? zaviyot? וכן הוא אומר, v'chen
hu omer, ומלאו כמזרק כזויות מזבח, u'mal'u k'mizrak k'zaviyot mizbe'ach, and
it will be filled like the מזרק, mizrak, like the מזרק, mizrak,
which is the bowl which catches, which holds all the blood that
you that you receive from when you slaughter a sacrifice, right, on
the, you know, on the corners of the altar. So זויות zaviyot
is used in both places, so it's talking about retaining blood, so
protecting, again, the virginity. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* reads it, that's one read
of רש"י Rashi *Rashi*, to me that's probably the פשט *pshat*, but
רש"י Rashi *Rashi* also suggests that it means that they don't have
sex when they're נדות *niddos*, and that's what it means. The sense
of blood and bleeding and that they do, and
it's actually I think significant then because הגמרא *hagmorah* talks even about
the marital
dynamics and that they're the ones that are maybe making sure that
everybody is keeping the סוכפות פתחיהן לבעליהן *sochfot pitchieihen le'ba'aleihen*
to read that their husbands might be might be trying to urge
them and they're refusing. You know they're the ones that are making
sure that they're not having sex when they're נדה *niddah*. רש"י Rashi
*Rashi* doesn't say that but he just he just says the first
part of it. איבעית אימא *Iba'is eima* and if you want you
can say מהכא *meihacha* from the following verse. מזווינו
מלאים מפיקים מזן אל זן *Meizaveinu melieim mefiqim mizan el zan*. So
literally that means that our storehouses are filled they're like coming out
with food upon produce. מחוטבות *mechutavot* so again the word here מזווינו
*mizveinu*
or כזווית *kezavit* and the idea of being filled. One also wonders
here if it's a play on the word of זן *zan* and
זנות *znus*. So that there's like רש"י *Rashi* says you have a
lot of sexual desire מפיקים מזן אל זן *mefiqim mizan el zan*
and nevertheless you're controlling the sexual desire. מחוטבות תבנית היכל *mechutavot tavnit
heichal*
hewn in the sort of image of the היכל *heichal* of a
castle or specifically of the היכל *heichal* of the המקדש *haMikdash*. אלו
ואלו מה מעלה עליהם הכתוב כאילו נבנה היכל בימיהם *eilu va'eilu mah
ma'aleh aleihem hakatuv ke'ilu nivnah heichal biyimeihem*. People that are able to
have mastery over their sexual desires, whether the men, both the men
and the women, if they succeed in that then it is like
the בית המקדש beit hamikdash, *Beis haMikdash* has been built in their
days. So that was a little bit of a digression here but
speaking in these whole sort of שיר השירים *Shir Hashirim* imagery.
The thing of the *Artscroll* does trans- basically saying that they're translated
Israel's time of maturity as reached time of spiritual maturity that's why
שדי נכונו ושערך צמח *shadaich nachonu ushe'areich tzimach*. שדי נכונו *shadaich nachonu*
as of reached time of spiritual maturity.
Okay, very nice.
Alright, now that we're talking it again within this sort of vein
about women and husbands etc., we look at the next פסוק pasuk.
*pasuk*. דבר השם אשר היה אל הושע Hoshea... בן בארי בימי עוזיה
יותם אחז חזקיה מלכי יהודה malchei Yehuda. *Devar Hashem asher hayah el
Hoshea ben Be'eiri bimei Uziyah Yotam Achaz Chizkiyah malchei Yehudah*.
People that are familiar other פסוקים psukim, *psukim* other נביאים *nevi'im* start
like that. חזון ישעיהו בן אמוץ אשר חזה בימי עוזיה יותם אחז
חזקיה *Chazon Yeshayahu ben Amotz asher chazah bimei Uziyah Yotam Achaz Chizkiyah*.
So הגמרא *hagmorah* actually makes that point. בפרק אחד נתנבאו ארבעה נביאים
*Beperek echad nitnab'u arba'ah nevi'im*. Four prophets
prophesied at the same time of יותם אחז וחזקיה *Yotam Achaz veChizkiyah*.
Were we going to see the time?
Yeah yeah yeah yeah, don't worry. וגדול שבכולן הושע Hoshea, *Vegadol shebechulan
Hoshea*, the greatest among the prophets was הושע Hoshea *Hoshea*, which is
pretty shocking since ישעיהו *Yeshayahu* gets 60 odd פרקים *prakim* and certainly
you think who knows even what's what's in הושע Hoshea... *Hoshea*. So
כדאמרינן *ked'amrinan* as the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says תחלת דבר השם בהושע
*techilat devar Hashem beHoshea*. The beginning of the word of God to
הושע Hoshea *Hoshea*. Now of course literal sense means this is the
first thing that God said to הושע Hoshea. *Hoshea*. But הגמרא *hagmorah*
interprets it as וכי בהושע דבר תחלה *Vichi beHoshea dibber techilah*? Was
הושע Hoshea *Hoshea* the first prophet God spoke to? Like תחלת דבר
השם *techilat devar Hashem*, the first speaking of God בהושע *beHoshea* was
with הושע Hoshea *Hoshea*. והלא ממשה עד הושע Hoshea כמה נביאים *Vehalo
miMoshe ad Hoshea kamah nevi'im*? Weren't there many prophets from משה Moshe,
*Moshe* to הושע Hoshea *Hoshea*? אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rabbi Yochanan. *Amar
Rabbi Yochanan* so said רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* תחלה לארבעה
נביאים שנתנבאו באותו פרק *techilah le'arba'ah nevi'im shenitnab'u be'oto perek*. The first
amongst the four prophets that prophesied at that time was with הושע
Hoshea, *Hoshea*. And it's presumably if it's the first it means it's
the most important. ואלו הן *Ve'eilu hen* and these are they הושע
Hoshea, ישעיה עמוס Amos? ומיכה *Hoshea Yeshayah Amos uMichah*. And they all
of them speak about these kings. Now תוספות *Tosafos* points out that
מיכה *Michah* doesn't exactly overlap with all four of the kings so
it's a little bit of a problem but anyway pretty close enough.
All four of these are at the same time. What kings? עוזיה
יותם אחז חזקיה *Uziyah Yotam Achaz Chizkiyah*.
Okay
so אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא להושע amar lo hakadosh baruch hu
l'Hoshea, *Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch Hu leHoshea*. Now we're going to talk
about הושע Hoshea *Hoshea* and this will be the tie in you'll
see somewhat to the theme we've been dealing with. Okay and all
of this by the way is completely no hint to this in
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* but it's all based on speculating what must
have preceded God's command to הושע Hoshea. *Hoshea* to take as a
wife a woman who was
a prostitute. So here's how הגמרא *hagmorah* fills in the back story.
You know it's sort of like the whole story with אברהם Abraham
*Avraham* and the father and the idols and all of that. It's
חז"ל Chazal *Chazal* trying to figure out why did God choose אברהם
*Avraham*? There's no back story. So here too it's trying to figure
out what was the back story? Right if you look at תוספות
*Tosafos* he basically says it explicitly. ממשאמר לו לקחת אשת זנונים דריש
שמסתמא כך אמר לו Amar lo, וכך השיב *Mimash'amar lo lakachat eishet
zenunim darish shemistama kach amar lo vekach heishiv*. There must have been
some back story prior. So here's the back story. אמר לו הקדוש
ברוך הוא amar lo hakadosh baruch hu, להושע *Amar lo Hakadosh Baruch
Hu leHoshea*. God says to הושע *Hoshea* בניך חטאו *banecha chata'u*
your children have sinned. So והיה לו לומר *vehayah lo lomar* הושע
*Hoshea* should have said back to God בניך הן *banecha hen*
they're your children בני חנונך הן *benei chanunecha hen* they're the children
of your chosen people of your grace בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב bnei
Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, *benei Avraham Yitzchak veYaakov*. If you're your kids God
don't blame this on me, and if they're the ones that you
should love, גלגל רחמיך עליהם, let your compassion, you know, overflow, roll
onto them. So so that's what he should have said.
Not only did he not say that, he didn't sort of tell
God to have compassion and that God should take a defend them,
God should recognize that they're God's children. אלא אמר לפניו, Ela amar
lefanav, what did he say to him? רבונו של עולם, Ribbono shel
Olam, כל העולם שלך הוא, kol ha'olam shelcha hu, Yours is the
entire world, if You don't like 'em, fine, take another nation. אמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu, מה אעשה לזקן זה, mah
e'eseh l'zakein zeh, what should I do with this elder? אמר לו,
Amar lo, so he
set God said to him, how am I going to make him
realize you don't give up on your children, no matter how much
they've strayed, you don't give up on them. אמר לו, amar lo,
so He said to him, לך וקח אשה זונה, lech ve-kach ishah
zonah, go take a woman who's a prostitute, והוליד לך בני זנונים,
v'holid lecha bnei zenunim,
and give birth to children of prostitution, which means that you're not
even certain whether they're your children or not. ואחר כך אמר לו,
v'achar kach amar lo, and then he said to him, שלחה מעל
פניך, shalcheha me'al panecha, now divorce her. אם הוא יכול לשלוח, im
hu yachol lishloach, let's see, I'll say that to him, let's see
if he's going to be able to divorce her. He thinks it's
so easy to give up on your wife, on your children. אף
אני אשלח את ישראל, af ani eshlach et Yisrael, and if he's
that's what he's asking me to do, to divorce myself from the
Jewish people. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, as the verse says, ויאמר השם אל הושע,
v'yomer Hashem el Hoshea, לך קח לך אשת זנונים, lech kach lecha
eshet zenunim, go take for yourself a wife of prostitution, וילדי זנונים,
v'yaldei zenunim,
and children of prostitution. וכתיב, u-chtiv, and it says, וילך ויקח את
גומר בת דבלים. v'yeilech v'yikach et Gomer bat Divlayim. He went and
he took this woman by the name of גומר בת דבלים. Gomer
bat Divlayim. So now we're going to have some fun interpreting what
those words mean. So so גומר, Gomer, so what does גומר Gomer
mean? אמר רב שהכל גומרים בה, Amar Rav she-hakol gomrin bah, all
finish in her men, so all men have sex with her. ובת
דבלים, u-vat Divlayim, and what does ובת דבלים u-vat Divlayim mean? דיבה
רעה בת דיבה רעה. dibah ra'ah bat dibah ra'ah. She has a
bad, דבלים Divlayim is in the plural, so she has a bad
reputation, the daughter of a woman with a bad reputation. שמואל אמר,
Shmuel amar, שמואל Shmuel says, שמתוקה בפי הכל כדבילה. she-metukah be-fi hakol
k'devilah.
Everybody,
she's as sweet to everybody, and it means this with a sexual
allusion, obviously not that she has a sweet
disposition, as a דבילה, dveilah, which is a pressed
dried figs, right. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, and
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says again very the very sort of blatant
sexual references here, שהכל דשים בה כדבילה. she-hakol dushin bah k'devilah.
All trample on her, which is actually a word used to refer
to, you know, דש dash is to thresh, which is used to
refer to, you know, sexual intercourse. Like דבילה, dveilah, like when they
make these dried figs, the way they sort of stomp on them
and press on them. Very coarse. Very, very coarse, right. So it's
actually, you know, all right. It's true, sometimes you get some of
these אגדתות aggadot which are quite explicit and sometimes you sort of,
you know, wonder also does this come up through an all-male culture
here of having of having this conversation.
And that would be coarse.
Right. Right. Right. And again, one does wonder, you know, if it's
this all anyway, the fact that there were no women as part
of this
conversation I think allows for some of that or made some of
that possible.
אמר רבי, Amar Rabbi, so now we have a slightly better version.
דבר אחר גומר אמר רבי יהודה, Davar acher Gomer amar Rabbi Yehudah,
שביקשו לגמור ממונם של ישראל, she-bikshu ligmor mamonam shel Yisrael, meaning it's
not talking about her, it's talking about at that time, it was
like all of they wanted the non-Jews wanted to finish the money
of Israel, meaning that they were that the Jewish wealth was being
taken away by by the non-Jews, right, was towards the end of
the בית ראשון Bayit Rishon period and they were constantly being besieged
and being and being looted, exploited. Exploited. Okay. בימיה, B'yameha,
during her during her time. So it's not about her at all,
it's not about sex at all. רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar,
בזזו וגמרו, baze-zu ve-gamru,
it's not that they wanted to, they actually did, right, they looted
and they complete and they took away all of the Jewish wealth.
שנאמר, she-ne'emar, כי אבדם מלך ארם וישימם כעפר לדוש, ki ibdam melech
Aram vayasimem ke-afar la-dush, because the king of Aram had wasted them
and made them like dust for trampling. Okay. So that's a little
talk about her name. Now. ותהר ותלד לו בן, Va-tahar va-teled lo
ben, she became pregnant and gave birth to a son. ויאמר השם
אליו קרא שמו יזרעאל, V'yomer Hashem elav kera shemo Yizre'el, call his
name יזרעאל, Yizre'el, כי עוד מעט ופקדתי את דמי יזרעאל על בית
יהוא, ki od me'at u-pakadti et d'mei Yizre'el al beit Yehu, because
in a very short time I will visit the sin of יזרעאל
Yizre'el which is יזרעאל Yizre'el remember it was the vineyard that אחאב,
Achav, you know, took and he murdered יזרעאל Yizre'el in order to
take the vineyard. I will visit the blood that was spilt on
the house of יהוא. Yehu.
והשבתי ממלכות בית ישראל, V'hishbatti mamlechut beit Yisrael, and I will return
or take into captivity the the kingship, the sovereignty of the house
of Israel. So you'll be all. taken away into exile. והשבתי v'hishpati
probably,
and not והשבתי v'hishpati I think and I will cause to cease,
I think I misread that. Does that have the נקודות nekudot there,
the one you have it? Is it והשבתי? v'hishbati? והשבתי, v'hishpati, I
will cause to cease, ממלכות בית ישראל. mamlechut beit Yisrael. ותהר ותלד
בן vatahar vateled ben and she actually so there's a little ellipsis
here, but this is all straight פסוקים, psukim but they just cut
out a few of they cut out like a half a פסוק.
pasuk, But anyway, she gave birth again and she gave birth she
became pregnant again and gave birth to a daughter. ויאמר לו, vayomer
lo, קרא שמה לא רחמה. kra shemah Lo Ruchama. הושע... God said
to him, call her name לא רחמה, Lo Ruchama, כי לא אוסיף
עוד ארחם את בית ישראל ki lo osif od arachem et beit
Yisrael I will no longer have compassion on the house of ישראל,
Yisrael, כי נשא אשא להם. ki naso esa lahem. Now that's a
difficult phrase because literally it means I will lift up, which usually
is a phrase about forgiving them. So רש"י says it's meant rhetorically,
to like, do you think I'll anymore forgive them? If you take,
I was looking at the JPS translation beforehand and it said meaning
of Hebrew uncertain,
which is what they do whenever they get a difficult phrase. Okay.
ותהר ותלד בן, vatahar vateled ben, and then she had another son.
ויאמר, vayomer, and God said קרא שמו לא עמי, kra shemo Lo
Ami, call his name not my nation, כי אתם לא עמי, ki
atem lo ami, you are not my nation, ואנכי לא אהיה לכם,
v'anochi lo ehye lachem, לא אהיה לכם, lo ehye lachem, and I
will no longer be for you. לאחר שנולדו לו שני בנים ובת,
leachar shenoldu lo shnei banim ubat, after the two sons and the
daughter had been born, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא amar lo hakadosh
baruch hu, להושע, so God said to הושע, לא היה לך ללמוד
ממשה רבך? lo haya lecha lilmod miMoshe rabecha? Hey, what did you
do, have these kids? You should have learned from משה, שכיון שדברתי
עמו, shekeivan shedibarti imo, from the time I began speaking with him,
פירש מן האשה, peirash min ha'isha, he separated himself from his wife.
אף אתה בדל עצמך ממנה, af ata bdal atzmecha mimena, you should
now divorce her, separate yourself from her. אמר לו, amar lo, he
said to him, רבונו של עולם, ribono shel olam, יש לי בנים
ממנה, yesh li banim mimena, I have children from her. ואיני יכול
להוציאה ולא לגרשה, ve'eini yachol lehotzia v'lo l'garsha, I can't get her
out of the house and or not to divorce her. Interesting that
those are separate things, meaning separation and then divorce. Anyway, I can't,
I can't kick her out. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lo
hakadosh baruch hu, so God said, ומה אתה שאשתך זונה ובניך בני
זנונים, u'ma ata she'ishtecha zona u'vanecha bnei znunim,
you, in your case, your wife is a prostitute, your kids are
children of prostitution, ואי אתה יודע אם שלך הם אם של אחרים
הם, v'ei ata yodeiah im shelcha heim im shel acherim heim, you
don't know even if they're your own children, and you don't want
to, you can't divorce yourself from your wife and your children. ישראל,
Yisrael, but the Jewish people, שהן בני, shehein banai, they're my children,
בני בחוני, bnei bechunai, the children of
my chosen, בני אברהם יצחק ויעקב, אחד מארבעה קנינים שקניתי בעולמי, echad
m'arba'ah kinyanim shekaniti b'olami, the one of my four special...
the משנה אבות Mishna Avot is five...
I know, four, the side reference is the משנה אבות. Mishna Avot.
The four special acquisitions I have in this world. תורה קנין אחד,
Torah kinyan echad, דכתיב, dichtiv, השם קנני ראשית דרכו, Hashem kanani reishit
darko, God has acquired me, the first of his way. By the
way, I should mention that קונה koneh in biblical Hebrew can also
mean to create, not just to acquire. קונה שמים וארץ, koneh shamayim
v'aretz, which is going to be the next one.
Right, קין, Kayin,
exactly, קניתי איש, kaniti ish, exactly. Right. שמים וארץ קנין אחד, shamayim
v'aretz kinyan echad, heaven and earth, דכתיב קונה שמים וארץ. dichtiv koneh
shamayim v'aretz. בית המקדש קנין אחד, beit hamikdash kinyan echad, דכתיב הר
זה קנתה ימינו. dichtiv har zeh kanta yemino. So oh my god,
we have all these things, we have תורה, Torah, heaven and earth,
the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash and ישראל, Yisrael, קנין אחד, kinyan echad,
דכתיב עם זו קנית. dichtiv am zu kanita. ואתה אמרת, v'ata amarta,
and so these are my children and the one, my special, and
you're telling me העבירם באומה אחרת, ha'avireim b'uma acheret, that I should
exchange them for another nation? כיון שידע שחטא, keivan sheyada shechata, so
therefore this was all a משל mashal to הושע about how he
should have, right, this is how the גמרא Gemara sort of reading
in the whole backstory about the whole purpose of the prostitute and
divorcing her and so on. So how could you have said such
a thing to me? Don't you know that you have to, you
know, love and own your children even when they stray? כיון שידע
שחטא, keivan sheyada shechata, since he knew that he sinned, sinned, עמד
לבקש רחמים על עצמו, amad l'vakesh rachamim al atzmo, he stood up
to ask for compassion for himself. Notice that, right? He's thinking about
himself. אמר Amar, לו, he said to him, הקדוש ברוך הוא, hakadosh
baruch hu, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar lo hakadosh baruch hu,
God said to him, you know, first thing you did, you did
something wrong, what are you worried about? About your own guilt? אמר
לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, what? Making הושע... I know, it's like you
don't, exactly, I was thinking the same thing. All you're worried about
is your... עד שאתה, ad she'ata, right? This is the problem. He
said I'm going to get rid of the Jewish people. What did
he care? He said, okay, get rid of them. He said you
made a mistake. He said, okay, forgive me. It wasn't about anybody
else, it was just about himself. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא, God
said, עד שאתה מבקש רחמים על עצמך, ad she'ata m'vakesh rachamim al
atzmecha, you're so concerned about your own self, asking compassion for yourself,
בקש רחמים על ישראל, bakesh rachamim al Yisrael, ask for the Jewish
people, that was what you should have been doing all
along. שגזרתי עליהם שלש גזירות בעבורך, shegazarti aleihem shalosh gezeirot ba'avurecha, because
of you, it's quite fascinating, it's making it all הושע's fault, all
of these things that God had said with the names of the
children, לא רחמה, Lo Ruchama, לא עמי, Lo Ami, all of that
is because of your sin. So עמד, amad, it's a good יום
כיפור Yom Kippur or post יום כיפור Yom Kippur message, right? Taking
responsibility, not just... מחילה mechilah so you can get forgiven and you
can go into יום כיפור Yom Kippur clean, but it's really taking
responsibility about correcting everything that you've done wrong. So עמד וביקש רחמים,
Amad u'vikeish rachamim, so he stood up and he finally asked compassion
for the Jewish people. ובטלה גזירה U'vatlah gezeirah and that succeeded and
now the edict that God had passed about was had been nullified.
I mean they were still going into גלות Galus but the harsh
terms about לא עמי, Lo Ammi, לא רוחמה, Lo Ruchama, that was
nullified. והתחיל לברכם V'hitchil l'varcham and he began to give to bless
them, God, שנאמר, shene'emar, והיה מספר בני ישראל כחול הים, V'hayah mispar
b'nei Yisrael k'chol hayam, well also God through that mouth of הושע.
והיה מספר בני ישראל כחול הים, V'hayah mispar b'nei Yisrael k'chol hayam,
they'll be like the sand of the sea. והיה במקום אשר יאמר
להם לא עמי אתם, v'hayah b'makom asher ye'amer lahem lo ammi atem,
instead of saying about them you are not my nation, יאמר להם
בני אל חי ye'amer lahem b'nei eil chai will be said to
them that you are the sons of the living God, the children
of the living God. ונקבצו בני יהודה ובני ישראל יחדיו V'nikbezu b'nei
Yehudah u'vnei Yisrael yachdav and they will be gathered together which is
the response of the to the curse of the גלות, Galus, right?
The גלות Galus was what was the פסוק pasuk: by the גלות?
Galus? It was
where was it?
Okay well let's see what was it?
לא רוחמה כי לא אוסיף עוד ארחם
את בית ישראל.
Lo ruchama ki lo osif
od arachem et beit Yisrael.
Well no the ארחם arachem we're going to get to. Oh, השבתי
ממלכות בית ישראל, Hishbati mamlachot beit Yisrael, so causing the kingship to
cease. So once again יהודה וישראל Yehudah v'Yisrael will gather together and
that will be the response to that. And in terms of the
לא רוחמה, lo ruchama, וזרעתיה, V'zartia, I will plant them לי בארץ
li ba'aretz in the land ורחמתי v'richamti את לא רוחמה et lo
ruchama and I will have compassion on לא רוחמה lo ruchama ואמרתי
ללא עמי עמי אתה, v'amarti l'lo ammi ammi atah, I will say
to those that I had said are not my nation you are
my nation. So actually I have to tell you that this is
part of what this is doing besides the obvious point of the
פסוק pasuk which sort of shows that God is going to say
in the end of the days you know we'll make up for
all of you know this will be all reversed, is it takes
the harsh judgment that God is saying לא רוחמה, lo ruchama, לא
עמי lo ammi and makes it that God never really said it.
Meaning makes it that it was all a lesson to הושע and
nothing that God ever wanted from the beginning. So it actually you
know is quite does a I think it's powerful in softening you
know that the initial prophecy as well even more than the פסוקים
psukim: do. It's not just it gets reversed. It's one thing to
say there's a period that you were לא עמי lo ammi and
now you're going to be עמי. ammi. And here it's saying no,
God's whole point was I'm never going to I'm never going to
divorce myself from them, they're always my children. I'm just doing this
to teach הושע a lesson.
Yes, phenomenally powerful. It means that the that the poetic license or
the literary flexibility that they allowed themselves shifted the theology completely.
Right, but it's true or the shift in theology allowed what they
right, allowed for their ability to right, the text
is so plastic.
Exactly. And makes it all about הושע as the source of all
of the bad, of all of this.
It also does something else. It's these children who are not who
have a stigma, God is saying I'm going to they will be
pure. Right, in the way they're stigma.
You mean like these בני זנונים? b'nei zinunim? Yeah, right. I mean
it's true God doesn't talk explicitly about about you know about those
but as a metaphor certainly that right? Even when you know exactly.
Exactly.
They're not going to be stigma.
Exactly, exactly. It becomes part of the theology of בני ישראל. b'nei
Yisrael. despite their sin and their punishment, I'm in love with them
and I will make good on my commitment. Right.
But again what it does is they've never stopped being my children
as opposed to a simple sense of reversing it.
It also extends to also
gives the
power
children who are born stigmatized.
Right, the whole issue of I mean that's I mean that's a
yeah I mean
take away the stigma.
Well that's a whole discussion by the way in the גמרא Gemara
about you know about at the time of משיח Mashiach about how
the the whole the ממזרים mamzerim and so on. Yeah so that
does definitely fit into this. Yes, Dov.
It also extends what you say, it gives all of this power
and the responsibility both to the נביא Navi to good
and bad and to the people, yeah.
Right, like if you hadn't if you had done it right in
the first place none of this would have happened.
Exactly. And I would say the other powerful thing is, again maybe
also particularly at this time of year is that even with all
the mistakes הושע made, get rid of them and then when he
was confronted with it all he could care about was himself. At
the end of the day, it was he, הושע, that managed to
reverse it all as well. So you know also that ability to
even if it takes you a while to wake up to your
responsibilities, in the end it can do some good. Yes.
But it was still, this was more than a century before the
first בית המקדש destroyed. Right, which is astonishing because
the negative prophecies did begin a good while before the actual destruction,
but yes. Alright, so now let's continue. The next edict.
Now exactly, now we continue.
So anyway, all this thing about you know obviously somewhat tying into
this whole theme here about wife and husband, connected you can see
sort of loosely to the theme that we introduced. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
I gotta find where I'm at. Okay, okay, atta. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, אוי לו לרבנות, oi lo l'rabbanut, woe to the
rabbinate, no, but but okay we can play with that one but
no, it means to authority, positions of authority. שמקברת את בעליה, she'mekaveret
et ba'aleha, it puts its those who take authority, its owners in
the grave. שאין לך כל נביא ונביא שלא קיפח ארבעה מלכים בימיו,
she'ein lecha kol navi v'navi shelo kipach arba'ah melachim b'yamav, you have
no prophet, whatever, it's the ones we're talking about, that did not
outlive four kings. שנאמר חזון ישעיהו בן אמוץ אשר חזה על יהודה
וירושלים בימי עוזיהו יותם אחז חזקיהו מלכי יהודה. Shene'emar chazon Yeshayahu ben
Amotz asher chaza al Yehuda v'Yerushalayim bimei Uziyahu Yotam Achaz Chizkiyahu malchei
Yehuda. So and all four of these prophets outlived four kings. So
you see that so this sense of taking authority can lead to
an early grave. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan. yes, אמר רבי
יוחנן. מפני מה זכה ירבעם בן יואש מלך ישראל להימנות עם מלכי
יהודה? Mipnei mah zachah Yerovam ben Yoash melech Yisrael le'himanot im malchei
Yehuda? In one of the listing of kings in הושע, we will
see that ירבעם בן יואש, Yerovam ben Yoash, who was from ישראל,
Yisrael, was counted with the evil king and was from ישראל Yisrael
and not יהודה, Yehuda, he was listed amongst the מלכי יהודה. malchei
Yehuda. Why was he listed? מפני שלא קיבל לשון הרע על עמוס.
Mipnei shelo kibel lashon hara al Amos. He didn't accept, he didn't
listen and believe in the לשון הרע lashon hara that was being
said about עמוס הנביא. Amos hanavi. Now let's spell this out. מנא
לן דאימני, Mena lan de'imni, where do you see he was listed?
דכתיב דבר השם אשר היה אל הושע בן בארי בימי עוזיהו יותם
אחז חזקיה מלכי יהודה ובימי ירבעם בן יואש מלך ישראל, Dechtiv dvar
Hashem asher hayah el Hoshea ben Be'eri bimei Uziyahu Yotam Achaz Chizkiyah
malchei Yehuda u'vimei Yerovam ben Yoash melech Yisrael, which is unusual, right?
If this person prophesied in יהודה, Yehuda, it would normally only list
מלכי יהודה. ומנא לן דלא קיבל לשון הרע? U'mena lan d'lo kibel
lashon hara? Where do you know that יואש Yoash did not accept
לשון הרע lashon hara on עמוס? Amos דכתיב וישלח אמציה כהן בית
אל אל ירבעם מלך ישראל לאמור קשר עליך, Dechtiv vayishlach Amatzyah kohen
Beit El el Yerovam melech Yisrael lemor kashar alecha, אמציה Amatzyah the
כהן kohen of בית אל, Beit El, which as רש"י says was
actually a idolatrous priest, אל ירבעם מלך ישראל לאמור קשר עליך, el
Yerovam melech Yisrael lemor kashar alecha, that there's a whole plot against
you. וכתיב כי כה אמר עמוס בחרב ימות ירבעם, V'chtiv ki cho
amar Amos bacherev yamut Yerovam, and עמוס Amos has prophesied that you
will die by a sword. אמר, so ירבעם Yerovam said, now this
is no longer in the פסוק, pasuk this is חז"ל Chazal, spelling
it out: חס ושלום! Chas v'shalom! אמר עמוס אותו צדיק, Amar Amos
oto tzaddik, God forbid that עמוס Amos should have said such a
thing and should be part of this plot against me. ואם אמר,
V'im amar, and if עמוס Amos. really did have this prophecy, מה
אעשה לו, Mah e'eseh lo, what should I do to him? שכינה
אמרה לו, Shechinah amrah lo, God told him that. So again, we
never find that he actually said that, but we're going to infer
it from the fact that he was included in this list. שכינה
Shechinah told who? עמוס. Amos עמוס that I would die by a
sword. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, אפילו בשעת כעסו של הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Afilu b'shat ka'aso shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu, even when God
is angry, זוכר את הרחמים, Zocher et harachamim, he remembers his compassion
or he remembers the attribute of compassion. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it says,
כי לא אוסיף עוד ארחם את בית ישראל. Ki lo osif od
arachem et Beit Yisrael. When it says לא רוחמה, Lo ruchamah, because
I will no longer have compassion on בית ישראל, Beit Yisrael, he
could have said because I'll have fiery anger against בית ישראל. Beit
Yisrael. When he says I won't have compassion, you're already referencing compassion.
And so even at the moment of anger, compassion is not forgotten.
רבי יוסי בר חנינא אמר מהכא,
Rabbi Yosi
bar
Chanina amar mehacha,
from the following פסוק: pasuk כי נשא אשא להם, Ki naso esa
lahem, because I will, again, meaning of Hebrew uncertain, I will forgive
them, at the end of a פסוק pasuk that I won't have
compassion on them. So רש"י says it means rhetorically: will I forgive
them? But the fact that you're even saying it, even rhetorically, means
that you are, it's still in your mind. ואמר רבי אלעזר, V'amar
Rabbi Elazar, now he also says, focusing on these פסוקים: psukim, לא
הגלה הקדוש ברוך הוא את ישראל לבין האומות, Lo higlah Hakadosh Baruch
Hu et Yisrael l'vein ha'umot, the only reason, this has now a
completely new tack but it's based on these פסוקים, pesukim the only
reason God made us exiled amongst the nations אלא כדי שיתווספו עליהם
גרים, Ela k'dei she'yitvasfu aleihem gerim, that we should have converts, we
should be spread amongst all the nations and people should know about
the Jewish people and that we should be able to have people
convert to us from amongst the nations. שנאמר, Shene'emar, which is amazing,
right? Missionary work. Well it says two things. First of all, גלות
galut is no longer a punishment for sin. I mean it's also
punishment for sin but ultimately it's all part of the divine plan
and it's all part about leading up to messianic period and everybody
finding out about God. And it's a very powerful notion about an
attitude towards converts. There are different statements in חז"ל, some of them
are concerned like, oh you have to be careful, they'll backslide, others
are extremely positive. Here it says the entire purpose about why we
are is because of the way that God values converts. Wasn't Rabbi
Eliezer ben Hyrcanus? גם רבי אליעזר הוא רבי אליעזר בן הורקנוס. Gam
Rabbi Eliezer hu Rabbi Eliezer ben Horkanos. Third century? רבי אליעזר בן
הורקנוס Rabbi Eliezer ben Horkanos I thought was earlier. Early. Second century.
I think he was even pre-חורבן, Churban, he was early. No no,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was one of רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva רבנים.
rabbanim. Right. So that would have been so that would have been
like first century, beginning of second. But this is the theme of,
oh interesting, the theme of Saul of Tarsus. Interesting. Of going around
the diaspora to get converts from the nations. Oh that's an interesting
putting it in that context. Strategy. Strategy. What the New Testament is
built on. All right, moving on. It actually though, like, if you
read, you know, historical Acts, you know, referring to that I haven't
placed it in that time frame, but, you know, clearly the world
was becoming much more monotheistic and interested in monotheism and leaving it
and it was a ripe period, you know, and people there were
all these people called like, you know, Judeophiles which were not Jewish
hadn't converted, and it was really circumcision which was the huge barrier.
So it's really, I mean, Paul drops the circumcision, I know, and
this is the Evangelion, the good news. I know, I know. But
it's amazing to imagine what opportunity we could have had if we
would have figured out the circumcision piece of that. Right. There isn't
an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that if a גר ger who
doesn't circumcise is still a גר ger if you do טבילה. tevilah.
We don't rule that way, but it's one imagines what would have
happened if we would have followed that approach. I mean because this
was a time that was ripe for it. Yes. It's also at
that time period. Now it's one thing to look back and say
about the גלות, Galus, right, what what the effect was, but at
the time to to have the vision to say, you know, this
is an opportunity. Right, and not right in the midst of a
very. You mean now that
we're living in a very privileged type of a גלות Galus that
it is, it's one thing to say, but when you're actually living
in a גלות Galus of oppression and to still see it as
the opportunity. Right, and not just the tragedy and the difficulty of
the expulsion. Exactly. Exactly. Just that vision. Exactly. Exactly. And it also
sort of also is a precursor to an idea I would say
about like, you know, being מעלה ניצוצות, maaleh nitzotzos, which is if
you think about it very similar. There's all this opportunity buried out
there in the world, right, and we have to go into גלות
Galus and we have to engage in the world in order to
raise it up. So the idea of finding the גרים gerim amongst
the nations to me I think there's a direct parallel with that
whole Lurianic idea. Yeah, and that's before the first Temple though, right?
Well, this statement of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer wasn't. It was after
the חורבן Churban of the second. But the פסוקים pesukim. he's going
to talk let's look at the פסוקים. Okay, שנאמר shene'emar as the
פסוק pasuk, says, וזרעתיה לי בארץ, U'zarticha li ba'aretz, I will plant
them to me in the land. כלומר אדם זורע סאה אלא להכניס
כמה כורין. Klumar adam zoreia se'ah ella lehachnis kama korin. You plant,
you know, one measure of grain and you hope to reap, you
know, many many barrels of grain. So you plant the Jewish people
and you hope that it's going to reap many fold that will
come back because they've been planted amongst these other lands. It's although
again it's quite funny because in the פסוק pasuk it's talking about
the redemption and planting them in the land of Israel. And this
is interpreting it as planting the seeds in the lands of exile.
רבי יוחנן אמר מהכא. Rabbi Yochanan amar mehacha. Now רבי יוחנן says
from the following verses now a few generations later, ורחמתי את לא
רחמה, Verichamti es Lo Ruchama, I will have compassion on those that
I have not that I have not. And the end of the
פסוק is, ואמרתי ללא עמי עמי אתה. Ve'amarti le'Lo Ami, Ami attah.
So לא עמי Lo Ami not just the people that I have
called not my nation, but the people that actually were not my
nation, the non-Jews, you will be עמי. Ami. So that is the
vision for for, you know, and גרות Gerus being tied in to
the idea of גלות. Galus. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, מאי דכתיב, mai
dechesiv, what's meant by the פסוק, אל תלשן עבד אל אדוניו, Al
talshen eved el adonav, do not, you know, sort of say evil
about a servant to his master, פן יקללך ואשמת, pen yekalelcha ve'ashamta,
lest the master
curse you and you'll be to blame. So, you know, don't go
don't go reporting
on slaves to their master.
וכתיב U'kesiv and the next verse says, דור אביו יקלל ואת אמו
לא יברך, Dor aviv yekalel ve'es immo lo yevareich, a nation that
its father will curse and its mother will not it will not
bless its mother.
משום דאביו יקלל ואת אמו לא יברך אל תלשן? Mishum de'aviv yekalel
ve'es immo lo yevareich al talshen? What's the connection of the
second פסוק to the first one? אלא, Ella, here's the point, אפילו
דור, afilu dor, even if it's an a wicked generation, שאביו יקלל
ואת אמו לא יברך אל
תלשן עבד אל אדוניו,
she'aviv yekalel ve'es immo lo yevareich
al
talshen eved el adonav, which is going back to the הושע
story, right, even if the Jewish people are so wicked that they're,
you know, father
and mother, God, they are doing this evil to they're cursing them
out, don't go again the other imagery, right,
is, you know, couple of images of God. God as king, God
as master over servants. So don't go saying bad things about the
Jewish people to God even if they actually have done these terrible
things. מנלן מהושע, Menalan me'Hoshea, from the exact story we just said
about הושע. אמר רבי אושעיא, Amar Rabbi Oshia, said רבי אושעיא, Rabbi
Oshia, מאי דכתיב, mai dechesiv, what's meant by the verse, צדקת פרזונו
בישראל, Tzidkas pirzono be'Yisrael, so פרזונו pirzono this is from the שירת
דבורה, Shirat Devorah, the righteousness of his פרזונו pirzono which is some
translate that as redemption in Israel. So we're going to reverse the
letters and do פזרון. pizron. צדקה עשה הקדוש ברוך הוא בישראל, Tzedakah
asa Hakadosh Baruch Hu be'Yisrael, God did a righteousness, good to Israel,
שפזרן בין האומות, shepizran bein ha'umos, that he scattered them between the
nations, presumably based on the previous idea but we're going to actually
introduce a new idea not related to גרים. gerim. והיינו דאמר ליה
ההוא מינא לרבי חנינא, Ve'hainu de'amar lei ha'hu mina le'Rabbi Chanina, like
a certain... A מין *min*, which often refers to as a Jewish
Christian, said to רבי חנינא *Rabbi Chanina*, אנן מעלי מינייכו *anan mallei
mineichu*, but we are better than you. כתיב בכו *ksiv bachu*, it
says by you, כי ששת חדשים ישב שם *ki sheishet chodashim yashav
sham*, that's talking about דוד *Dovid* in אדום Edom, *Edom* that he
was there for six months and he wiped out like, you know,
all, you know, all of the אדומים *Edomim* of that place. So
you, you were masters over a place and look how you used
your power, you wiped out the people. ואילו אנן *ve'ilu anan*, and
as far as we, איתנחו גבן *itnechu gaban*, you're amongst us. Now
it sounds like it's actually a Roman talking and we're going to
have that at the end, you know, again, I don't know if
this, this could have been post, what's his name, Constantine. When was
רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*? No, רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* was the end.
רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* was post-Constantine. Yeah, רבי חייא Rabi Chiya *Rabbi
Chiya* and רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* were the, yeah, so, so there's,
אושעיא *Oshaya* was a תנא *Tanna*, that would have been a century
before Constantine. No, I'm not sure, this is all in Aramaic. I
don't think, I think this is an אמורא *Amora*, I don't think
this is a תנא *Tanna*, it's all in Aramaic. אושעיא *Oshaya* was
the מלקט *melaket* of the ברייתות *braitos*, right? No, there's, that's, there's
רבי חייא Rabi Chiya *Rabbi Chiya* and רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* who
did the, who did the ברייתות *braitos*, but there's a, isn't there
a רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya* who was an אמורא *Amora*? I don't
know, I don't know, Constantine at the beginning of the... Okay, I
don't know. Anyway, because I'm just trying to, because it sounds like
we're talking about the Romans, we'll see in a moment, but the
מין *min* normally does not refer to Romans. So anyway, that's what
you guys did, ואנן *ve'anan*, and by us, איתנחו גבן *itnechu gaban*,
you guys are with us. The Jewish people are here in all
these Roman lands, כמה שני *kama shani*, for many years, ולא עבדינן
לכו מידי *velo avdinan lachu midi*, we didn't do anything to you.
I don't know about exactly anything, but okay, we certainly didn't wipe
you out. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to him,
רצונך יטפל לך תלמיד אחד *retzonecha yitapel lacha talmid echad*, is it
if it's your desire, I will have a certain student sort of
take care of you. Meaning, I'll give you, that's such an easy
question, I'll get my student to answer it. My בעל עגלה *baal
agala*, exactly. נפל ליה רבי אושעיא *nefal lei Rabbi Oshaya*, so רבי
אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, there's the רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, sort of, you
know, came, was, took over this case. אמר ליה *amar lei*, he
said to him, משום *mishum*, you know why you don't wipe us
out? משום דלא ידעיתו היכי תעבדו *mishum delo yadeitu haichi taavdu*, you
don't know how to deal with us. תכלינו כולהו *tahlinu kulu*, should
you wipe us all out? איתנחו גבייכו *itnechu gabaichu*, we're not all
amongst you, we're scattered, we're scattered. So מה דאיכא גבייכו *ma de'ika
gabaichu*, and those of us that are among you, I mean it's
very difficult to read this because it makes you think about obviously
the Holocaust and the high density of Jews in certain locations, and
how you know, whatever. So but those of us that are among
you, קרי לכו מלכותא קטיעתא *kari lachu malchuta ktiasta*, if you want
to wipe us out, you'll be called a murderous kingdom. So which
is a little funny because I mean, okay, but דוד *Dovid* wiped
out those אדומים *Edomim*, so it's, but maybe saying you're not doing
it out of morality, you're doing it out of reputation. Although, you
know, the Romans actually what they would do is they would come
in and they would wipe out nine out of every ten males
in certain locations when they were afraid that there would be rebellions,
that's where decimate comes from. Decimate is one out of ten. Right.
So actually in certain times, you know, the Romans actually would be
quite murderous, you know, in certain regions. And decimation was actually of
their own armies after a rebellion. Oh, when their armies rebelled, that
was it? 90% would be ordered to kill the 10%. I thought
decimate was that they killed that 90%. You're saying they killed 10%?
They killed 10%. They killed 10%, it was ordered to make the
army more brutal. Interesting. I thought, okay. I'll check this out, I
don't doubt you, but I thought it was also certain regions that
were rebelling. In general, the Romans left indigenous populations. Right, but there
were certain, I thought there were certain rebellious regions. Okay, I might
be... and רבי אושעיא *Rabbi Oshaya*, according to some, רבי אושעיא *Rabbi
Oshaya* lived in the 3rd and 4th century, so he would have
been a contemporary. Yeah, there you go. Okay, so it could be
Romans and after they had become Christian. But didn't they try to
destroy the Jewish people with the destruction of the Second Temple? What?
The destruction of the Second Temple, they tried to destroy the Jewish
people, right?
No, they took over the Temple, they didn't try to wipe out
the whole people. אמר ליה *amar lei*, so he said back to
him, why don't you check up where the word decimate comes from
while you're at it? I'm serious. אמר ליה *amar lei*, he said
to him, גפא דרומאי *gappa d'romai*, which some say means the capital
of Rome. I thought it means like the wing, like Rome is
an eagle, as, you know, the Romans, they carried the eagle as
their symbol. How does it translate גפא *gappa* there? אלוהי רומאי *elohei
Romai*, that's what, anyway, I saw something translated as capital. What does
the Artscroll say? Either wall or... either wall, okay, anyway, something of
the Romans. בהא נחתינן ובהא סלקינן *beha nachetinan uveha salkinan*, that's what
we go down and come up with, meaning that's what we're always
debating, how to kill you guys out without getting it to ruin
our reputation. Okay, I found something, a comment on גפא *gappa*. What?
That there's different... different interpretations. It could be the capital, it could
be a god.
So it's a note.
Clearly it's a note.
Okay, it could be because... It could be from the Greek agape
which is love. Right. Okay. Let's just finish till the end. תני
רבי חייא, רבי חייא taught.
רבי חייא taught. מאי דכתיב, Mai de-chtiv, what's meant by the verse?
אלהים הבין דרכה והוא ידע את מקומה, Elohim hevin darkah ve-hu yada
et mekomah, God knows its way and God knows its place. יודע
הקדוש ברוך הוא את ישראל שאינם יכולים לקבל גזרות אכזריות, Yodea hakadosh
baruch hu et yisrael she-einam yecholim lekabel gezerot achzariyot, God knows that
the Jewish people could not take the evil decrees, the cruel decrees
of אדום, of the Roman, of the Romans. לפיכך הגלם לבבל, Lefikach
higlam le-vavel, another explanation for גלות galut because the Romans were in
Israel, but if we had stayed in Israel we would have been
under their rule and we would have been subject, we know about
the types of persecution. So therefore they went to בבל Bavel where
Jews had it a lot better in בבל. Bavel. דאמר רבי אלעזר
לא הגלה הקדוש ברוך הוא את ישראל לבבל אלא מפני שעמוקה כשאול,
De-amar Rabi Elazar lo higla hakadosh baruch hu et yisrael le-vavel ela
mipnei she-amukah ke-sheol, as deep as the שאול, sheol, as the, you
know, the depths. שנאמר, Shene'emar, מיד שאול אפדם, mi-yad sheol efdem, from
שאול, sheol, the underworld, אפדם, efdem, I will redeem them. So therefore
they had to be in בבל Bavel in order to be to
have the sense of being redeemed, rather it's a little funny, God
said it so then he had to do it. So anyway, מיד
שאול אפדם, mi-yad sheol efdem, ממות אגאלם, mi-mavet eg'alem, I will redeem
them from death because שאול sheol was often seen as the underworld
where people would go after they die, after they died. רש"י said
that therefore God would redeem them more quickly because they were in
such a place. So maybe we should all go back to בבל.
Bavel. I don't know. רבי חנינא אמר מפני שקרוב לשונם ללשון תורתן.
Rabi Chanina amar mipnei she-karov leshonam lileshon toratan. No, if, well this
doesn't explain why not Israel, but if you're going to go anywhere
other than Israel, בבל Bavel at least they spoke Aramaic, it was
a very, it was a cognate language. רבי יוחנן אמר מפני ששגרם
לבית אמם, Rabi Yochanan amar mipnei she-shigram leveit imam, they were going
back to their mother's house. This might tie way back to the
כלה kallah going back to her father's house because אברהם came from
ארם נהרים, Aram Naharaim, which is בבל. Bavel. משל לאדם שכעס על
אשתו. Mashal leadam sheka'as al ishto. What? אור כשדים. Ur Kasdim. Well,
actually it's מחלוקת רש"י ורמב"ן. machloket Rashi ve-ramban. We could talk about
that later. אור כשדים Ur Kasdim is not... okay. The questions where
do you originally come from and anyway, okay, either Aramaic. משל לאדם
שכעס על אשתו, Mashal leadam sheka'as al ishto, so a man gets
angry on his wife, again going back to the discussion at the
beginning of the דף, daf, להיכא משגרה, leheicha meshagrah, where does he
send her? לבית אמה, Leveit imah, her mother's house. So I guess
when she's having a good, when it's good she goes to her
father's house, I don't know the difference between mother's and father's house.
Well, right. והיינו דרבי אלכסנדרי, Ve-hainu de-Rabi Alexandri, that's like רבי אלכסנדרי
Rabi Alexandri says. דאמר שלשה חזרו למטעתן, De-amar sheloshah chazru lemata'atan, three
returned to their, you know, their planting, to where they, to their
cribs. אלו הן: ישראל, Elu hen: yisrael, the Jewish people; כסף מצרים,
kesef mitzrayim, the money of the Egyptians that they took when they
left; וכתב לוחות, u-ketav luchot, and the script on the לוחות, luchot,
which is coming from God. ישראל הא דאמרן, Yisrael ha de-amran, Israel
as we said, when they went to גלות galut they went back
to בבל. Bavel. כסף מצרים דכתיב ויהי בשנה החמישית למלך רחבעם עלה
שישק מלך מצרים על ירושלים, Kesef mitzrayim de-chtiv vayehi bashanah hachamishit lamelech
rechavam alah shishak melech mitzrayim al yerushalayim, and he basically he looted
it and took all the gold and silver away, also picking up
on those themes we had before about the wealth being stripped at
the end of that period. וכתב לוחות דכתיב ואשברם לעיניכם, U-ketav luchot
de-chtiv va'ashabrem le'eineichem, I broke them to your eyes. What does it
mean in your eyes, in front of your eyes? תנא לוחות נשברו,
Tana luchot nishberu, the actual tablets were broken. ואותיות פורחות, Ve-otiot porchot,
and like you know you saw a magical thing in front of
your eyes, you saw that the actual letters flew back to God.
More of this tomorrow. Okay. That was some.